Guide to the Osborn Family Papers 1832-1936 MS 474
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Henry Fairfield Osborn papers
  Subseries II.3, Speaking engagements and publications, includes programs and announcements of some of HFO's lectures, and drafts of a talk ("What a Girl Can Do") and article on the topic of suitable occupations for women. Also included are articles by HFO on religion and evolution and on the history of the New York Zoological Society, which HFO founded (now known as the Wildlife Conservation Society, it manages the Bronx Zoo, Central Park Zoo, Prospect Park Zoo, Queens Zoo and the New York Aquarium). There are also several folders of notes and drafts, and several folders of correspondence with Charles Scribner's Sons, who published multiple books by HFO.
  Subseries II.4, Professional appointments and biographical information, contains material relating to HFO's tenure as President of the American Museum of Natural History (1908-1933). This includes correspondence and papers relating to the "Bumpus Affair" of 1910-1911, a conflict over exhibits between HFO and AMNH director Dr. H.C. Bumpus which resulted in the latter's resignation, and correspondence concerning the Roosevelt Memorial (cornerstone laid in 1931). Also included is one folder of material relating to HFO's appointment as a professor at Columbia University, and some biographical articles and notes.
  Subseries II.5, Journals, consists primarily of annual leather-bound datebooks kept by HFO between 1899 and 1935. These contain both professional and personal notations, regarding appointments, engagements, travel and scientific observations, birthdays of friends and families, and significant events. Clippings, calling cards and similar materials were sometimes inserted next to related entries; to retain context, these have not been removed so researchers should be careful when handling.
  There are also a few more extensive travel and expedition journals: 1867-68, 1871 (Europe), 1879 (Coburg/London), 1885 (Germany), 1913 (Western United States), and 1922 (China/Mongolia).
  - Subseries II.1: Correspondence and related materials
    - General correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1879, 1884-1889, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Correspondents include Alexander Agassiz (son of Louis Agassiz), Edith Roosevelt, and Benjamin Sharp.
    - General correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1890-1899 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Includes a letter from John Muir while on the Alaska Harriman Expedition in 1899.
    - General correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1901-1913 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Includes 1912 correspondence between HFO and Jacob Schiff regarding the issue of immigration restriction.
    - General correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1914-1920 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - General correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - General correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1926-1931 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - General correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1932-1936 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osbon to William Berryman Scott, 1876-1882 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      For transcriptions of these letters, see Box 30, Folder 3.
    - Correspondence of Henry Fairfield Osborn and William Berryman Scott, 1883-1892 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      For transcriptions of these letters, see Box 30, Folder 4.
    - Correspondence of Henry Fairfield Osborn and William Berryman Scott, 1893-1914 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      For transcriptions of some of these letters, see Box 30, Folder 4.
    - Correspondence of Henry Fairfield Osborn and William Berryman Scott, 1921-1925 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II.2: Associations and honors
    - Memberships "A" (includes Argentina and Austria), 1910's-1930'sm (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Includes Andrew Ward Association and Aryan Society.
    - Memberships "A" ("American"), 1910-s-1930's (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Includes American Ethnological Society, American Eugenics Society, and American Genetic Association.
    - Memberships "B" (includes Belgium), 1910-s-1930's (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Memberships "C" (includes China, Cuba and Czechoslovakia), 1910-s-1930's (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Memberships "D"-"F" (includes France), 1910-s-1930's (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Memberships "G" (includes Great Britain), 1910-s-1930's (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Memberships "H"-"I" (includes Italy), 1910's-1930's (Box 21, Folder 9)
      Includes Immigration Restriction League, International Commission of Eugenics, and International Congress of Americanists.
    - Memberships "N", 1910's-1930's (Box 22, Folder 1)
      Includes New York Zoological Society
    - Memberships "P" (includes "Persia"), 1910's-1930's (Box 22, Folder 2)
      Includes correspondence relating to "hoax" Puritan Memorial organization
    - Memberships "R" (includes Russia), 1910's-1930's (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Memberships "S" (includes Sweden) (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Memberships "T"-"Z", 1910's-1930's (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Memberships -- Committees, 1910's-1930's (Box 22, Folder 6-7)
    - Memberships -- Mayor's Committee of Welcome, 1913-1935 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Medals and decorations, 1910's-1930's (Box 22, Folder 9-10)
    - Clubs, 1910's-1930's (Box 23, Folder 1)
      Includes The Explorers Club and the Zodiac Club (correspondence, invitations and membership cards)
    - Honorary degrees, 1910's-1930's (Box 23, Folder 2-3)
    - Princeton University, 1877-1930 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Princeton University, 1932-1935 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Princeton University -- Printed material and ephemera, 1870's-1930's (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Tributes and letters of appreciation, 1910's-1930's
    - Tributes -- Chamber of Commerce, 1929 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Tributes -- 70th Birthday, 1927 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Tributes -- 75th Birthday, 1932 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Tributes -- 76th and 77th Birthdays, 1933-1934 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Retirement from AMNH, 1933 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Subseries II.3: Speaking engagements and publications
    - Speaking engagements -- programs and printed material, 1910's-1930's (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Speaking engagements and articles -- "What a Girl Can Do", 1935 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Articles and requests for articles relating to religion and evolution, 1910's-1920's (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Published and unpublished histories of the New York Zoological Society by Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1900-1935 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Drafts and notes, undated (Box 25, Folder 3-4)
    - Correspondence with Charles Scribner's Sons, 1925-1930 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with Charles Scribner's Sons, 1931-1936 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Subseries II.4: Professional appointments and biographical material
    - AMNH: Appointments and financial documents, 1910's-1930's (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - AMNH: Bumpus Affair, 1910 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - AMNH: Bumpus Affair, 1910-1911 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - AMNH: Roosevelt Memorial, 1920's-1930's (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Columbia University
    - Checks and receipts for money paid to H.A. Whiteside, 1922-1923 (Box 26, Folder 6-7)
    - Articles and clippings relating to Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1910's-1930's (Box 27, Folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence and notes relating to biography of Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1934-1936, undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
      See also Box 30, Folder 7.
  - Subseries II.5: Journals
    - Journals, Datebooks/Diaries, 1867-1868, 1871, 1899-1921 (Box 28)
      Separated Materials Note
      Several maps and other loose materials were removed from Osborn's 1913 journal and re-housed in Box 31, Folder 2.
    - Datebooks/Diaries, 1922-1935 (Box 29)
    - Travel diary, Coburg, 1879 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      For transcription of this diary, see Box 30, Folder 8.
    - Travel diary, Germany, 1885 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Transcription of 1871 journal of trip to Europe (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Notes from expedition to Tennessee, undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Itinerary, 1933 trip to England and France (Box 27, Folder 5)
- Series III: Transcriptions and oversize material
  This series consists mainly of transcriptions of primary material found elsewhere in the collection, including some of Osborn's correspondence and a few journal excerpts. Also included is a typewritten extract relating to Osborn and the Princeton Scientific Expedition to the West in 1877 from "W.B. Scott: Materials for an Autobiography." There are also several pieces of oversize ephemera, including a 1931 certificate of appreciation issued to Henry Osborn as one of the Founders of the Save the Redwoods League.
  - Transcriptions, Henry Fairfield Osborn letters to William H. Osborn (father), 1879-1890 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Transcriptions, Henry Fairfield Osborn letters to William Church Osborn (brother), 1883-1886 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Transcriptions, Henry Fairfield Osborn letters to William Berryman Scott, 1876-1882 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Transcriptions, Henry Fairfield Osborn letters to Edward Poulton and Frank Speir, 1880's-1890's (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Extracts from W.B. Scott Materials for autobiography, undated (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Biographical information, Henry William Osborn and Henry Fairfield Osborn (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Transcription, Travel diary, Coburg, 1876 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Transcription, Diary excerpts, 1901-1903 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Ephemera and notes (Box 31, Folder 1)